<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iniunctions exhibited by Iohn by gods sufferance Bishop of Norwich in his first visitacion beginning the seconde daie of Maye in the thirde yeare of our soueraign Ladie Elizabeth by the grace of God Quene of England, Fraunce and Ireland. Defendour of ye faith. [et]c. vnto all &amp; singuler the diocesans of the diocesse of Norwich so farre as they concerne any of them.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1561</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Norwich. Bishop (1560-1575 : Parkhurst)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120553</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 422:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iniunctions exhibited by Iohn by gods sufferance Bishop of Norwich in his first visitacion beginning the seconde daie of Maye in the thirde yeare of our soueraign Ladie Elizabeth by the grace of God Quene of England, Fraunce and Ireland. Defendour of ye faith. [et]c. vnto all &amp; singuler the diocesans of the diocesse of Norwich so farre as they concerne any of them.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1561</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Norwich. Bishop (1560-1575 : Parkhurst)</author>
                  <author>Parkhurst, John, 1512?-1575.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Day, dwelling ouer Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted ad [sic] London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum gratia et priuilegio Regias Maiestatis.</note>
                  <note>Includes Interrogatories, which are an enlarged version of those in STC 10133.5--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Iniunctions exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by Iohn by gods ſufferance Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Norwich in his firſt viſitacion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the ſeconde daie of Maye in the thirde yeare of our ſoueraign Ladie Elizabeth by the grace of God Quene of England, Fraunce and Ireland. Defendour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith. &amp;c. vnto all &amp; ſinguler the dioceſans of the dioceſſe of Norwich ſo farre as they concerne any of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jmprinted ad London by Iohn Day, dwelling ouer Alderſgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CVM GRATIA ET PRIVILEGIO RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIAE MAIESTATIS.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21251:2"/>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21251:2"/>
            <head>Iniunctions exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Iohn by Gods ſufferaunce Biſhop of Norwich in his firſt viſitacion begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſeconde daie of Maye in the thirde yeare of our ſoueraign Ladie Elizabeth by the grace of God Quene of England, Fraunce and Ireland. Defendour of the faith &amp;c. vnto all and ſinguler the dioceſans of the dioceſſe of Norwich ſo farre as they concerne any of them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euery parſon, vicare and Curate, doo ſo order the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſeruice within the city of Norwich &amp; other lyke places where be diuers pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh churches in one toune, that it maye be doon on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daie, by nine of the clok, before the beginning of the ſermon, where any is appointed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al the people after como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayers be doon in their pariſh churches may reſort the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to heare the ſermon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Item that as many of them as be entred into orders, do ſaie the morning and euening praiers dailie in Engliſhe or Latten, either openly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natelie, that they may be the more reddie in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Item that they ſee vnto their Clerks &amp; Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, if they doo ring at the buriall of the deade,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21251:3"/>noone or curpheue, they ring but one peall, &amp; that berie ſhort, omitting all other vnneceſſarie rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings as it is preſcribed by order taken herin.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Item that they neither ſuffer the Lordes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be hanged and decked like an aulter, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſe any geſtures of the popiſh maſſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of miniſtracion of the communion, as ſhifting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke, waſhing, breathing, croſſing or ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Item that they baptize not children on the wourking daies, or when the congregacion is not come together, except it be thought that eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Ieoperdie require the contrarie.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Item that they marie no yonge folkes, except they examin them before, whether they can ſaye, the articles of the Chriſtian faithe, the Lordes prayer and the ten commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: and if they can not: then to ſtay them from going forwards, till they can ſaie them. Likewiſe that they exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min the godfathers and godmothers, when they come to baptize childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame points: ſecretly, &amp; modeſtly, bearing with the age of ſom parſons. For howe can they be ſureties for an other to be inſtructed in that faith, which they can not ſkill of themſelfes. Thirdlie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſuffer none to come to the holie communion, except they alſo knowe the ſame neceſſarie points of Religion.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Item y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they marie none before dewetime, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is before ſix of the clock in the ſomer, and ſeuen in the winter, at what tyme the broade daie light doth appeare.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Item that they preache theyr ſermons limited by the Q. Mayeſties Iniunctions that is euerie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21251:3"/>moneth one orels at the leaſt wies get them to be preached, ſo that they them ſelfes preache foure tymes in the yeare in their own parſones beeing habled thereto by theyr ordinarye if they can not preache then to reade ſom homely ſet out by the Queens Maieſtie.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Item that they with ſuche diligent trauail induſtrie and conference do euerie weke reade &amp; peruſe two chapiters of the newe teſtament and ſtudie the ſame that they may be able to anſwere to all matters conteyned therin with the trewe vnderſtanding therof to begynne with Sainct Mathewes goſpell and after with ſaint Iohns, and ſo conſequentlie till they begon ouer and ſo to the Epiſtles. This to begynne in Auguſt next, &amp; to make accompt to ſuche as bithe ſaied reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d father ſhalbe appointed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt tweſdaie of euery moneth following. And beſides this they ſhal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cauſe euerie quarter one ſermon at the leaſt to be preached at ther beneficesbi ſome learned prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cher till they be hable to preache them their ſelfes. To this taſke as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chapters the curates alſo be enioyned though they haue no benefices.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Item that they teache the Catechiſme eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſondaie and euery holidaie one howre at the leaſte before euening prayer and to beginne the ſame the firſt ſondaie in Auguſt next &amp; ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue euerie ſondaie and holydaie.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Item y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they warne the parents &amp; maiſters to cauſe theyr children and youthe to learne the Catechiſme, either in ſcholes or els at home ſo as they may be examined by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter euery ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daie
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21251:4"/>and holydaie that they may make anſwere to the miniſters ſtanding in the pulpet dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of them and this ſhalbe doon inmediatlye after the laſt peale to euening praier.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Item that they requyre the yonge folkes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried to reſorte to the hearing of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mined and rendering of the Catechiſme to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that they by hearing may learne the ſame, &amp; therby (beſides diſcharge of their dewty towards God) auoid worldlie rebuke and ſhame whyche ſhuld happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them, if they ſhoulde be reiected from mariage for ignoraunce of the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith, the Lordes Prayers, and the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. Exhorting alſo thelder maried folkes to be preſent bothe for the good example of the youthe &amp; alſo to learne them ſelfes, by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring if they by reaſon of euill educacion in tyme of ignoraunce, haue not been ſufficientlie inſtructed in tymes paſt.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> Item y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſee the places filled vp in walles orells where, where imagies ſtode, ſo as if ther hadde been none there. The ſtones foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or other places, frames or Tabernacles deuiſed to aduaunce Imagerie, holy waterſtones alſo to be quite and clean taken away and the places where they were ſet, comelie and decentlie to be made vp with conuenient expedicion, orells to declare to the ordinarie the lettes &amp; ſtaies therof as ſone as may be.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> Item that euerie Parſon, vicarre, Curate and reader, ſhall euery quarter ones, reade ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in the pulpet the Quenes maieſties Iniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21251:4"/>and alſo theſe preſent Iniunctions with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion hereunto annexed, and beſides that, get him a copie of theſe Iniunctions and ſet them vp by the laſt of Septembre in ſome conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place of theyr quier there to remaine ſtill to be ſeene of them that lyſt to reade them.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15</hi> Item that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maiſter, pryeſt, and other gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of all hoſpitals be vigilant and look dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, as wel to the wel ordering and godly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing of the ſik &amp; ſore people within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame hoſpitals: as alſo to the vertuous and godli edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion of the children and other youth there, ſo as they may be taught to folow &amp; fauour the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere veritie of almighty God, as it is now mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſet forthe by the Quenes moſt excellent Maieſtie &amp; that they themſelues alſo be folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers therof.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Interrogatories.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether the parſons, vicare, curate, or reader doth reade the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruice with a lowde, diſtinct, and treatable voyce.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Whether the leſſons epiſtels and goſpels be redde or ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſo as they may be plainli barde of the people.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Whether the parſone or vicare preach or cauſe to be preached in his churche euery moneth one Sermon.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Whether euery parſon or vicare preache in his owne parſone one ſermon euery quarter, if there be no ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they reade the homilies plainly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21251:5"/>and diſtinctlie according to the Iniunction.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> Whether to the vttermoſt of their wit power knowledge &amp; learning they do with out colour or diſſimulacion, declare four tymes yearelye in their ſeuerall ſermons or exhortacions that the power of the Biſhop of Rome and all other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyn power, are iuſtlie taken away.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> Whether they doo exhorte the people to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the poore after the homelye when they reade the ſentences exhorting the Almoſe.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> Whether they teache the youthe of theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe the Lordes prayer, the articles of the faith, the tenne commaundements and the Catechiſme euerie ſundaie and holidaie.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> Whether they and theire churche wardeyns haue prouided in theyr pariſh a Byble in the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt volume, and Eraſmus paraphraſis vpon the newe Teſtament.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> Whether they declare to their pariſhes any thing to thextolling or ſetting fourthe of vayne and ſuperſticious religion.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> Whether the parſon or vicare being abſent hath left vppon his benefice an honeſt learned &amp; expert Curate.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11</hi> Whether any miniſter or prieſt in the tyme of trouble haue deuorced him ſelf from his wife and whether his wyfe hath been maryed to any ò<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man ſithen, or that he himſelf hath maried any other woman without iudgement of the Churche.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12</hi> Whether the Prieſtes, and deacons ſaye daylie the morning and euening ſeruice, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lye or priuatelye.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21251:5"/>
                  <hi>13</hi> Whether ani y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> toke orders in king Edwards daies not contented with that, were ordered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in Quene Maries daies.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14</hi> Whether the parſon or vicare, or any for him hath bought his benefice or hath come by it by ſimonie fraude or deceipte.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15</hi> Whether the parſon or vicare haue more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices then one.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16</hi> Whether any of your benefices be vacant, &amp; howe longe they haue ſo been &amp; who is the patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17</hi> Whether ther be any laye or temporall men not being within orders or children that hath or enioyeth any benefice or ſpirituall promocion.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18</hi> Whether there be any patron that ſuffereth any benefice to be vacant and taketh the tythes and other dueties to him ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> Whether any parſon, vicare or Curate geue any euell example of lyfe, whether they be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t parſones, dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kards, haunters of tauernes, alehouſes or ſuſpect places: dycers, tablers, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſwearers or vehemently ſuſpected therof.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>20</hi> Whether they haue receiued any parſone to the holie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion openlie knowne to be out of charitie or diffamed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome notorious crime before he hath made ſufficient recompence for his wronge or euell doing.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <hi>21</hi> Whether they haue a fitte and decent table to miniſter the communion on.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <hi>22</hi> Whether the parſon or vicare being not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident vpon his benefice geueth the fourty parte therof, to the poore of the pariſhe.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <hi>23</hi> Whether any parſon or vicare findeth but a
<pb facs="tcp:21251:6"/>reader vnder hym where he ſhoulde fynde Miniſter.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <hi>24</hi> Whether the chauncell, the bodie of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe churche or chapell, the parſonage and vike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage houſe, and other belonging to the ſame: be in good reparacions, and whether the better co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueringes of any of them haue been pulled of and worſe ſet in the place and by whome.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <hi>25</hi> Whether they celebrate the communion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leſſe nombre then foure or thre comunicantes at the leaſt in ſuche pariſhes wheare there be xx. parſones of diſcretion &amp; in greater pariſhes with out a greater nomber.</p>
               <p n="26">
                  <hi>26</hi> Whether if there be more Prieſtes in any churche then one: they doo all comunicate with the miniſter when the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion is celebrate.</p>
               <p n="27">
                  <hi>27</hi> Whether that any reader being admitted but to reade: taketh vpon him to baptize, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; to celebrate the Lords ſupper or to diſtribute the Lords cup.</p>
               <p n="28">
                  <hi>28</hi> Whether they baptize children in any other daies then the ſundaies and holidaies except it be thought need that they ſhould be baptized at home.</p>
               <p n="29">
                  <hi>29</hi> Whether they haue maried any without banes aſking, or if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parties maried be of diuers pariſhes, whether they haue maried them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out certificat from the parſone or parſones where they where aſked: or haue maried any y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be out of their owne pariſhes not licenced therunto, or hath not openly denounced theyr certificat or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly at the tyme of mariage or hath
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21251:6"/>maried any parſon not in due place or conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent tyme.</p>
               <p n="30">
                  <hi>30</hi> Whether they haue exhorted yong folke to abſteine from priuie contractes and not to mary without the conſente of ſuche their parentes and freends as haue authoritie ouer them.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <hi>31.</hi> Whether they haue admitted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, any of an other pariſhe except they be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers without the licence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they came.</p>
               <p n="32">
                  <hi>32</hi> Whether that there be any y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> preacheth out of their owne pariſhes not licenced therunto, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels taketh vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to preache being not ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor licenced therunto.</p>
               <p n="33">
                  <hi>33</hi> Whether the maiſter and gouernours of the hoſpitall within Norwich and other hoſpitals w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the dioceſe of Norwich doo looke diligentlie to the well orderyng and godlie inſtructing of the ſicke &amp; ſore people within the ſame hoſpitals.</p>
               <p n="34">
                  <hi>34</hi> Whether the youth within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame hoſpitalls be taught to fauour and folowe the ſincere very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of almightie God as it is now ſet forth by the Queenes moſte excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the duetie of churche wardeines.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether they haue prouided a comelie and honeſt pulpet to be ſet in a comeli place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Whether al aulters, images, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water ſtones, pictures, paintings, as of Thaſſumption of the bleſſed virgin, of the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending of Chriſt into the virgin in the fourme of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21251:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>a lytle boy at Thanunciacion of the Aungell, and al other ſuperſticious and dangerous monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts eſpeciallie paintings &amp; Imagies in walle, boke, cope, Banner or els where, of the bleſſed trinitie or of the father (of whom ther can be no Image made) be defaced and remoued out of the churche and other places and are deſtroyed &amp; the places where ſuch impietie was: ſo made vp, as if there had been no ſuche thing there.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Whether that any Imagies, beades, bokes of ſaruice, or veſtiments not alowed by lawe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or in any place, by whome and where they be reſerued.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Whether they knowe any man that refuſeth to contribute to the Almes of the poore as a thing not rightlie appointed and diſcorageth other fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche charitable Almes.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> Whether the Churchwardeynes haue proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a ſtrong cheſt, for the poore mens boxe and haue faſtened it in a fytte place.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> Whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche money comyng of mouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtockes money geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fynde torches, tapers, lamp light not payde out of any lands, be implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed to the poore mens boxe or no?</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> Whether the Churchewardeynes of euerie pariſhe doo dulie levye and gather of the goods and lands of euerie ſuche parſone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cometh not to his owne pariſhe churche vpon the ſondaies and holly daies and there heare the deuin ſeruice and Gods worde redde and preached xii. d. for euery ſuche offence, and whether thei haue diſtributed the ſame money to the poore.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21251:7"/>
                  <hi>8</hi> Whether there be a regiſter had and kept faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of Chriſtenings and Burials.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ For Scholemaiſters and theyr office.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether any Scholemaiſter take vpon him to teache not alowed by the ordinarye.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Whether thei moue and teache theyr children duelie to reuerence &amp; loue the trewe religion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is nowe ſet fourth.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Whether they teache their children ſuche ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences out of the ſcripture as may frame them to Godlynes.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Whether they teache any other gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer then ſuche as is appoincted by the Quenes Maieſties Iniunctions annexed to the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ For Clarkes and theyr dutie.</head>
               <p>WHether that the ſonge in the Churche be modeſt and diſtincte ſo deuiſed and vſed that the ditte may plainly be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Whether they vſe to ſing any nomber of pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, dirige lyke, at the buryall of the deade or do any other thing otherwiſe then it is appointed by the comon order of the ſeruice boke.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Whether they vſe to ring oft or longe peales at the buryall of the dead or vſe muche iangling in feſtiuall daies in ringing none or curphew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:21251:8"/>
               <head>¶ For the people and theyr duetie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether there be any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that mocketh or ieſteth at the deuine ſeruice, or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters therof or ſpeaketh any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g bi ieſt or earneſt to the diſpiſing, dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion or letting therof.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Whether any man hath burned or cauſed the holy Byble to be burned, torne or defaced or hath conueyed it out of the Churche that it ſhould not be redde of the people.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Whether any pariſhoner denieth to receyue the ſacraments and other rites eccleſiaſticall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke aucthorized by como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> authority.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Whether any man is knowen to haue ſaide, or heard maſſe ſithens it was abrogate by lawe, wherher any man maketh any ſinging cakes to ſay maſſe with all, reſerueth veſtiments, ſuperal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, maſſe bookes or other inſtruments of this ſuperſticion.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> Whether any doo deferre theyr children to be baptized be yond y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next ſundaie or holidaie after their birth and vpon what cauſes they do ſo.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> Whether any be ſo haſtie to baptize their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that hauing no nede they will not tary till y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next holiday that the child may be partaker of the prayers of the whole churche, then preſent.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> Whether any haue maried with in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of conſanguinitie prohibited by the lawes of God, ether whether any maried without thoſe degrees, haue vnlawfully forſaken theyr wyfes or huſbands or maryed others.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:21251:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>8</hi> Whether any man kepeth in his houſe any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed Images namely ſuche as be remoued out of the churche, or S. Iohns head. S. Catheryn, S. Nicolas or ſuche lyke.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> Whether any body vſeth beades laten pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers or any other prayer bookes then that be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by publike authority to be vſed.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> Whether there be any that mainteyneth any hereſie or falſe opinion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Goddes word.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11</hi> Whether there be any that exerciſeth ſorcery, ſooth ſaying, whytchcraft or ſuche lyke cuxyous artes.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12</hi> Whether there be any incontinent parſones druncardes, ſwearers, blaſphemers of the name of God, raylers at religion or fautie in any other enormouſe crime or vehementlie ſuſpected of the ſam.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13</hi> Whether there be any that neglecteth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorte comonly to his pariſhe churche and there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydeth orderlie and ſoberlie during the tyme of ſeruices.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14</hi> Whether there be any that vſeth byeng, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, dreſſinge, carying to and fro of cloth, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyth his occupacion, geueth himſelfe or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his to labour bodelie or to attende their oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupacion on the ſaboth daie, hindring bothe them ſelfes and theyrs, therby to learne goſtly things.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15</hi> Whether therbe any that walketh or talketh in the Churche at ſeruice tyme or goeth out with out vrgent nede.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16</hi> Whether therbe any bodye otherwiſe occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied at ſeruice time then to here &amp; marke the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:21251:9"/>orels ſuffer theyr children to diſturbe the diuine ſeruice.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17</hi> Whether any parſon of diſcretion hath not comunicate thriſe in the year and in eſpecially at eaſter laſt paſt who they be and what be theyr names.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18</hi> Whether any hath maried the banes not being laufully aſked before except he had a diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion of the ordenarie.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> Whether fathers, mothers, maiſters, and dames ſendeth out their children and ſeruauntes to be inſtructed in the Catechiſme on ſondaies and holidaies.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>20</hi> Whether vinteners or they th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> kepe vitay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes doo ſell meate or drynk in tyme of ſeruice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſermons.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21251:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
